Guide to the Theressa Gay Papers, 1946-1960
Department of Special Collections
Theressa Gay Papers,
1946-1960
Special Collections M0274
Gay, Theressa.
10.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Theressa Gay, ca. 1975.
Biographical Note
Theressa Gay was born on Febrary 3rd, 1894 in Illinois. She received her undergraduate degree from the University of Wisconsin. She moved to Wyoming shortly after graduation and lived in several western states including Montana and California. She did graduate work at the University of Montana on the history of the trans-Mississippi West. She received her M.A. from the University of California, studying under Dr. Herbert E. Bolton. She wrote her Master's thesis on the Establishment of Territorial Government in Montana. She also did post-graduate work at Stanford University under Dr. Edgar Robinson.
Her varied professional career has included teaching, doing library work, and, most notably, performing research for her own publications and on the behalf of other history scholars. She taught high school history in various towns in Montana and Washington; in California, at Berkeley High School and at Castilleja School in Palo Alto. She has also worked as a teaching assistant at the University of Montana and at Stanford University. She also taught English as a Second Language for the Palo Alto Adult Education Program. She also worked as a school librarian and held several library staff positions, including Stanford University, when she was not teaching or working on research projects.
Theressa Gay's most significant professional accomplishments were her contributions to the field of historical scholarship, most significantly to that of the history of the California Gold Rush. Her book, James W. Marshall, the Discoverer of California Gold (Georgetown, Calif.: Talisman Press, 1967), represents the culmination of more than thirty years of research. Those familiar with the history of the California Gold Rush, are aware that James Marshall's discovery of gold at Sutter's Mill resulted in one of the greatest gold rushes in modern history. This event which had enormous consequences for the economic and social history of the State of California, has had more written about it than any other single event in California history. However, until Theressa Gay's biography was published in 1967, only one other biography had been written about James Marshall. The first book was an official biography which was written at Marshall's request in order to pay the debts that he had incurred in his later years. According to reviews that were written after the publication of her biography in 1967, Ms. Gay's biography is well-documented and does much to dispell the myths and half-truths that surrounded Marshall and his life. This work goes well beyond being a simple biography, and gives scholars a detailed insight into life during a significant period in California history.
In addition to the biography on Marshall, Ms. Gay also published a book entitled Life and Letters of Mrs. Jason Lee, First Wife of Reverend Jason Lee of the Oregon Mission (Portland, Or.: Metropolitan Press, 1936); and number of periodical articles, including, The California and Australia Gold Rushes, As Seen by Amos S. Pittman. She also collected songs from the Gold Rush which were written by gold miners, popular song writers of the day and by dance-hall entertainers, from 1848 to 1855. This was an independent project during which she collected about two hundred songs. These songs, as well as research and manuscript material used by Ms. Gay in preparing her publications, form the core of her personal papers collection.
Scope and Content
The bulk of this collection consists mainly of research notes, correspondence and manuscript material pertaining to Theressa Gay's historical research on the California Gold Rush. This collection also includes materials relating to other areas of historical research as well (see contents listings for specific topics); some biographical material and teaching files. The focus of this collection are the original manuscript of Thressa Gay's biography of James W. Marshall, and a group of about two hundred Gold Rush Songs that she collected. The papers in this collection reflect her work over a period of approximately fifteen years, from about 1946 to 1960. It comprises about ten and a half linear feet of material.
Series Description
- SERIES I: PERSONAL AND BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION
  The first series contains biographical notes and partial listings of Ms. Gay's professional experiences. Also included is a datebook/calendar from 1947.
- SERIES II: CORRESPONDENCE, 1946 TO 1960
  The second series consists of Ms. Gay's correspondence; mostly incoming correspondence, but some copies of outgoing correspondence as well. Most of the letters pertain to inquiries regarding research on the California Gold Rush, but a small number deal with other topics as well. There is personal correspondence included here as well, but these letters often also pertain to Ms. Gay's research. Some of the individual correspondents include Warren T. Russell, a Gold Rush historian; and Hesley S. Davis and Mother Lee, descendants of several of Ms. Gay's research subjects.
- SERIES III: SONGS OF THE CALIFORNIA GOLD RUSH, 1845-1855
  The third series contains the songs collected by Ms. Gay, on the California Gold Rush. The songs are filed in alphabetical order by title. Also included is Ms. Gay's Plan for Work, which outlines her collecting strategy. A complete alphabetical listing of the songs colleced by Ms. Gay is included here, as well as research and bibliographic notes.
- SERIES IV: BIOGRAPHY OF JAMES W. MARSHALL
  The fourth series contains the original, handwritten manuscript for Ms. Gay's biography of James W. Marshall. Also included are a number of chapter revisions from the manuscript, and a periodical review of the biography from the California Historical Quarterly.
- SERIES V: RESEARCH NOTES AND MATERIALS (BY SUBJECT)
  The fifth series contains the bulk of the collection. It is divided according to subject area, and then is subdivided by specific topic. The first section consist of research notes for the James Marshall biography: some of the folder headings in this section reflect chapter titles from the Marshall biography. The section which follows consists of Gold Rush material, some of which overlaps with material on James Marshall. Other sections in theis series include: California--Other Topics; Miscellaneous Topics (which includes research notes on the history of the Pacific Northwest, on American Politics of the 20th Century, and other miscellaneous topics.)
- SERIES VI: TEACHING FILES, 1947 TO 19--
  The sixth series consists primarily of course materials and notes from two history courses for which Theressa Gay was a teaching assistant at Stanford University's History Department. These courses included History 132 (The Westward Movement) and History 169 (The History of California.) Also included is one item from the Adult Education course that she taught for the Palo Alto Unified School District.
- SERIES VII: PUBLICATIONS AND PRINTED MATERIALS
  The seventh series contains pamphlets, fliers, tourist maps, newsclippigs and other printed materials that Theressa Gay collected during the course of her research. Of particular interest are the various pamphlets and fliers relating to the California Gold Rush, and 20th century political campaign materials. This series also includes periodicals and newpaper articles pertaining to Theressa Gay's historical research; and history book trade list publications that were used as sources for research materials.
- SERIES VIII: PHOTOGRAPHIC MATERIALS
  The final series of this collection consists of a variety of photographic materials, including black and white photographs, negative photostats and microfilm. Most of these materials pertain to the James Marshall, or the California Gold Rush, but photographs having to do with other subject matter is also included.
Container List
- SERIES I: BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL
  - Biographical and resume notes (Box 1, Folder 1,2)
  - Datebook/Calendar from 1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- SERIES II: CORRESPONDENCE, 1946 to 1960.
  - Incoming (1946 to 1960):
    - A (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - B--F (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - G--H (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - I--L (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - M--P (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - R--Z (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
    - Hensley S. Davis (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Mother Lee (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Evelyn Mick (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Gerald D. Nash (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Warren T. Russell (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
    - Warren T. Russell (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Outgoing (1947-1960):
    - Copies of outgoing correspondence (by date) (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    - Invoices (Box 2, Folder 6)
- SERIES III: SONGS OF THE CALIFORNIA GOLDRUSH, 1845-1855
  - Plan for Work and List of Songs, A-Z (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - Songs, A--C (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
  - Songs, D-F (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Songs, G-I (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
  - Songs, J-L (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Songs, M-O (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
  - Songs, P-R (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
  - Songs, S-U (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Songs, V-Z (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Untitled Songs (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
  - Song Lists (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
  - Research and Bibliographic Notes (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
  - Research and Bibliographic Notes (Box 3, Folder 1)
- SERIES IV: BIOGRAPHY OF JAMES W. MARSHALL
  - Biography of James Marshall--Manuscript
    [Note: Ms. Gay's original enumeration is shown here in brackets; numbering without brackets reflects the published version)
    - Prologue, The Ringing of the Bells [I] (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Chapter I. [A Boy Grows Up] Boyhood Family Traditions [II] (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Chapter II. Adventuring Westward [III] (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Chapter III. California Bound [IX] (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Chapter IV. Lord of New Helvetia [V] (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Chapter V. Marshall at Sutter's Fort [VI] (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Chapter VI. Helping Manifest Destiny [A Son of N. J.] [VII] (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Chapter VII. Building a Sawmill [VIII] (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Chapter VIII. Gold! [IX] (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Chapter IX. The Secret is Out [X] (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Chapter X. The Rush is On! [XI] (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Chapter XI. Yellow Fever... [XII] (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Chapter XII. Culloma, 1848-1849 [XIII] (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Chapter XIII. Marshall and the Miners [XIV] (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Chapter XIV. A Famous Sawmill's Fate (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Chapter XV. Prospecting Around [XV] (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Chapter XVI. A Coloma Vinyardist [XVII] (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Chapter XVII. As Seen About Coloma [XVIII] (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Chapter XVIII. Mining Again [XIX] (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Chapter XIX. Lecture Tour [XX] (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Chapter XX. A State Pension [XXI] (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Chapter XXI. Kelsey Years XXII] (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Chapter XXII. Marshall and his Neighbors [XXIII] (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Chapter XXIII. Marshall on Parade [XXIII] (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Chapter XXIV. The Final Summons: [XXV] (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Chapter XXV. A Fuss Over Me [XXVI] (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Bibliography [Incomplete] (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript & research notes (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Chapter revisions (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
    - Periodical review of biography (Box 4, Folder 6)
- SERIES V: RESEARCH NOTES AND MATERIALS (BY SUBJECT)
  - James W. Marshall:
    - Aid for Marshall (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
    - Death of Marshall (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
    - Early Years in Missouri (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
    - Early Years in New Jersey (Box 4, Folder 13-14)
    - Estate (Box 4, Folder 15-16)
    - Gold Discovery (Box 4, Folder 17-18)
    - James W. Marshall Museum--Catalogue (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Lecture Tour (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Marshall County Proposal (Box 4, Folder 21-22)
    - Marshall on Parade (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Marshall's Monument (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Marshall's Monument (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Military Career (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Property--Litigation (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
    - Property--Sale of the Mill (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Property--Sale to Samuel J. Hensley (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Prospecting Around (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Reminiscenes About Marshall (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
    - Tarson's Life of Marshall (Box 5, Folder 10-11)
    - Vineyard in Coloma (Box 5, Folder 12-13)
    - What Cheer House (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Misc. Notes (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Misc. Notes, (notecards) (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Gold Rush in California
    - Amos Pittnam Letters (Box 5, Folder 17-18)
    - California Gold Rush Centennial (Box 5, Folder 19-20)
    - Coloma (Box 5, Folder 21-22)
    - Difficulties of Mining during the Gold Rush (includes correspondence with Gerald Nash) (Box 5, Folder 23-24)
    - Emigration (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - El Dorado County Archives (Box 5, Folder 26-27)
    - El Dorado County History--Misc. (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - George Johnson's Coloma Notebook (excerpts) (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Gold Mining in California (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Hanging of Irish Dick Crone (1850) (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Indian Difficulties in Coloma (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
    - John Sutter and His Fort (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
    - John Sutter's Diary (excerpts) (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - John Sutter's Personal Reminiscences (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Misc. Notes from Missouri Newspapers (Box 6, Folder 10-11)
    - Mormons in California (Box 6, Folder 12-13)
    - Other First Discoveries (Box 6, Folder 14-15)
    - The Secret Is Out (Box 6, Folder 16-17)
    - Yellow Fever, California Variety (Box 6, Folder 18-19)
  - California--Other topics
    - Bank of California: (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - --Mark Hopkins Correspondence, (photostats) (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - --William Ralston Correspondence, (photostats) (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - --Ralston correspondence (other) (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - --Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 7, Folder 4-6)
    - Botanical Gardens in California (Box 7, Folder 7-8)
    - California's Centennial (Box 7, Folder 9-10)
    - Christmas in Old California (Box 7, Folder 11-12)
    - En route to California (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Indian Difficulties in California (Box 7, Folder 14-15)
    - Land Use in California (includes correspondence to Gerald Nash) (Box 7, Folder 16-17)
    - Orientals in California (Box 7, Folder 18-19)
    - Pacific Squadron (Box 7, Folder 20-21)
  - Misc. Topics:
    - American Politics (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Jason and Daniel Lee (includes correspondence from family members) (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Diary of G. W. Melhorn, CSA (transcript) (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous research notecards (Box 15)
    - Miscellaneous research notes (Box 8, Folder 3-7)
    - U. S. and International Politics (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
- SERIES VI: TEACHING FILES, [1946--]
  - Teaching Assistant Files (Stanford University History Department):
    - Course notes and materials from History 132 and History 169 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Teaching Files (Palo Alto Adult Education Program):
    - Course material (item) (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8, Folder 12)
- SERIES VII: PUBLICATIONS AND PRINTED MATERIALS
  - Pamphlets and Fliers:
    - Gold Rush (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - American Politics--Campaigns, etc. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Maps and Travel Guides:
    - Gold Rush Country (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Misc. (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
  - Book Catalogs (Box 9, Folder 5-8)
  - Misc. items and recipes (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Newsclippings (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Newsclippings (Box 11, Folder 1-9)
  - Newsclippings (Box 12, Folder 1-12)
  - (Box 13, Folder 1-11)
- SERIES VII: PHOTOGRAPHIC MATERIALS
  - Microfilm and negatives (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Microfilm and negatives, (os) (Box 16)
  - Photographs and photostats (Box 10, Folder 2-6)
  - Photostats (Box 14, Folder 1-10)
  - Microfilm